<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kairos Cliodynamics</title>
    <link>http://kairos-research.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kairos Cliodynamics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 15:13:19 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://kairos-research.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Showcase</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/showcase/</guid>
      <description>As a collective and as individuals, we participate in a broader process of scientific enquiries. Here is an overview of our academic work :
Our publications Guénin&amp;ndash;Carlut, A. (2020). Cognition in eco and naturalism. https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/ERCZ6 (In process at Intellectica)
Guénin&amp;ndash;Carlut, A. (2020). Beyond State—Drafting a prospective anthropology. https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/EHQJS (In preparation)
Our talks 2020 january 16 : Is cognition individual ? A complex system perspective, in Cognivence BAF talks, ENS Ulm</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naturalism in the social sciences : a short review</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/state-of-the-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 15:13:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/state-of-the-art/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Naturalising&amp;rdquo; social sciences ? Naturalism is a philosophical and scientific position stating that all observable things belong to the same realm of existence, and follow the same fundamental set of identifyable &amp;ldquo;natural laws&amp;rdquo;. Natural scientist typically work toward the exposition and formalisation of these laws, notably through the construction of predictive theories and their test in reproducible experimental settings. While this perspective has been highly successful in fields such as astronomy, chemistry, and geology, it is at the moment marginal in the social sciences and generally understood to be inadapted to the complexity of human beings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Low Tech against the State</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/low-tech-against-the-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 20:14:44 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/low-tech-against-the-state/</guid>
      <description>Cumulative cultural evolution and the maladaptive loss of knowledge Humans are characterised as a specie by their exceptional ability for social learning. Indeed, while they are mostly unable to understand causally the tools they use, they are however able to identify who to learn from and what features to reproduce in a way that allow the maintenance and progress of their adaptive knowledge 1. In turn, this ability means that social structure &amp;amp; the sheer size of societies constrains the evolution of technology 2 : more densely connected societies with a diversity of subpopulations are better able to maintain complex technologies such as ironwork than sparser or homogenous societies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cliodynamics, or the study of historical processes</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/historical-processes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 21:42:23 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/historical-processes/</guid>
      <description>Cliodynamics and science-fiction Cliodynamics is a field which very existence is controversial. Among all subdisciplines of cultural evolution, &amp;ldquo;history as a science&amp;rdquo; is the only one that consistently draw criticism when it is discussed - while its claims are by no mean stronger than those of paleoanthropological history or cultural attraction theory. Two points may stroke as odd in such arguments : the first is that the very same thesis receive very different treatment if they are labeled &amp;ldquo;cliodynamics&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cultural evolution&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;historical anthropology&amp;rdquo; ; the second is that critics of cliodynamics rarely answer any specific point made by cliodynamicians, instead attributing them claims akin to Asimov&amp;rsquo;s psychohistory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond State</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/beyond-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 21:56:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/beyond-state/</guid>
      <description>States today seem to exert an undisputed hegemony over the governance of human societies. It seems natural to project their predominance on the past as well as on the future, or at least to imagine the world outside state regulation as wild, uncultivated, and unfit for human life. However, and against what seems obvious, States constitute a marginal and fragile mode of organization on the scale of human history. In the light of the work on the evolution of human societies over long period of time, it even seems doubtful whether these institutions will be able to maintain their dominance in the near future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognition in eco, Cognition in vitro</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/cognition-in-eco-cognition-in-vitro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 21:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/cognition-in-eco-cognition-in-vitro/</guid>
      <description>The cognitive sciences are an interdisciplinary research project, built in the context of Macy&amp;rsquo;s conferences which established the computationalist paradigm comparing the functioning of the human mind with that of a computer. Sixty-seven years later, this project seems to have exploded between many competing approaches 1, presumably under the abundant evidence of fundamental discrepancies between human cognition and artificial computation. It appears indeed that cognitive agency emerges from complex interactive dynamics between an agent and their environment 23456 rather than innate algorithmy, a feature that remains essentially absent in experimental or theoretical cognitive psychology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CartoWiki</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/cartowiki/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/cartowiki/</guid>
      <description>We aim to build a website presenting a dynamic map of the world through time on the basis of a collaborative architecture of data collection. A year and a half within the project, our data mainly concerns the geography and demography of political entities such as cities and states. Our long term goal is to add many type of data relative to ecology, religion, economy, material culture&amp;hellip;
This work can be accessed on the CartoWiki website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural ecology of belief, practices and institutions</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/cultural-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/cultural-ecology/</guid>
      <description>We are working to study how culture itself builds the niche where culture evolves, or in other words how multi-level interaction between cultural traits build through time the landscape where these same traits evolve. This amounts to study social forms, such as a specific form of ritual, as autonomous organisms engaging in niche construction. For exemple, the invention of a new media could enable the creation of new cultural traits giving more influence to its adepts, and indirectly reinforce its own hegemony.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural evolution seminar</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/cultural-evolution-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/cultural-evolution-seminar/</guid>
      <description>We organised a seminar presenting an overview of cultural evolution research with the ENS Ulm Département d’Études Cognitives. Initially programmed from February to April 2020, it was postponed indefinitely due to the coronavirus crisis.
The goal of the seminar is to give non-experts a general picture of contemporary research relative to human evolution, including its main results, its contemporary debates, and its institutions. In this optic, we first present the general framework of evolution theory, then show how humans evolved to become a cultural species.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epistemology and Ontology of cultural evolution</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/epistemology-and-ontology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/epistemology-and-ontology/</guid>
      <description>We are interested in the philosophy of cultural evolution, and how it informs philosophical theories of knowldege (epistemology) and representation of what exists in the world (ontology). We study more particularly the way we build knowledge in cultural evolution theory (its epistemology) and what fundamental entities it invokes to represent the world (its ontology). We argue those are two important elements to the integration of cultural evolution theory to pragmatic action, as they respectively allow to integrate its results to a broader body of knowledge, and to translate it into mundane intuition about the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kairos Cliodynamics - Lyon</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/communities/lyon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/communities/lyon/</guid>
      <description>The Lyon community is organising a serie of seminars on the philosophy of cultural evolution, in collaboration with the ENS Lyon-affiliated Junior lab of epistemology and social ontology.
Want to participate or ask questions ? Mail us at kairoscliodynamics@disroot.org while specifying [Kairos - Lyon] in your object !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kairos Cliodynamics - Marseille</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/communities/marseille/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/communities/marseille/</guid>
      <description>The Marseille community is working to adapt Ostrom and Wilson&amp;rsquo;s work on collective autonomy to higher eduction, and is providing a dynamic map of socio-political evolution during human history
Want to participate or ask questions ? Mail us at kairoscliodynamics@disroot.org while specifying [Kairos - Marseille] in your object !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kairos Cliodynamics - Paris</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/communities/paris/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/communities/paris/</guid>
      <description>The Paris community is organising an introductory seminar to cultural evolution in collaboration with the ENS Ulm Département d&amp;rsquo;Études Cognitives. In addition, it is organising regular informal presentations on subjects relative to cultural evolution.
Want to participate or ask questions ? Mail us at kairoscliodynamics@disroot.org while specifying [Kairos - Paris] in your object !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kairos Journal</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/kairos-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/kairos-journal/</guid>
      <description>The Kairos journal is a minimalist journal of cultural evolution. Its focus is to synthetise theoretical knowledge of social networks, institutional change, collective cognition or other dimensions of cultural evolution, and bridge it with pragmatic insight about human societies. The range of topics we adress is intentionally wide as we aim to ground a systemic understanding of how human interactions drive societies rather than adavance a specific theoretical framework. We are especially interested in discussing what scientific knowledge means from a cultural evolutionary perspective, and how it may guide action in shifting societies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kairos meetings</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/kairos-meetings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/kairos-meetings/</guid>
      <description>We organise regular meetings around the presentation of specific articles or research in cultural evolution, cliodynamics, or human evolution. These events are based on voluntary participation of students and young researchers willing to present research articles, or more generally to share their reflexions in a friendly and informal context. In addition, they are an occasion for those interested in cultural evolution to gather around food and drinks, and either participate actively in the discussion or just sit back and listen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pedagogical project</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/projects/pedagogical-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/projects/pedagogical-project/</guid>
      <description>We are working to develop a method to improve education and learning in University based on Multi-Level Selection theory, which focuses on how competition between social groups facilitate the emergece of cooperation within these groups. We are mainly inspired by Elinor Ostrom&amp;rsquo;s work on how humans organise to govern common resources in collective autonomy 1, and its numerous applications in attempting to build inclusive and functional institutions - in particular in the context of the Evolution Institute 2.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
