<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kairos Cliodynamics</title>
    <link>http://kairos-research.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kairos Cliodynamics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 20:53:24 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://kairos-research.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 20:52:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/research/</guid>
      <description>We work on articulating cultural evolution research as a tool for governing societies, and in particular to help navigate the upcoming crisis of dominant institutions. Our interests range from the deep history of political and economic institutions to the structural causes of innovation, resilience or revolution. We are especially concerned with research regarding the role of knowledge and ideology in political integration, and the meaning of scientific models.
We are considering the publication an annual bulletin on the matter of cliodynamics and its epistemology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transmission</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/transmission/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 20:53:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/transmission/</guid>
      <description>We work to synthesise and diffuse of relevant research regarding cultural evolution and its epistemology (that is, how it builds knowledge and what this knowledge means), which we will publish here, submit to general audiences press, or articulate into public talks.
We have also undertaken to apply cultural evolutionary paradigm to the transmission of knowledge, by adapting Ostrom&amp;rsquo;s Core Design Principles and the following Good Behaviour Game to help sustainable cooperation networks to emerge within student groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About us</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 20:17:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/about/</guid>
      <description>Kairos Cliodynamics is a grassroots movement of researchers and students of cultural evolution - that is, the science of what processes drive human cultural change and stability. Our purpose is to build, diffuse, and apply knowledge from this discipline to harness its power to help navigate the upcoming late Anthropocene era.
We want to build an open and integrative science that is oriented toward informing the governance of human societies. While we agree to work with academic institutions, we recognise their limitations in terms of reach and inclusivity, and chose to organise as an informal collective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 20:51:32 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>Want to join us, share ideas, or ask what we&amp;rsquo;re up to ? Mail us at kairoscliodynamics@disroot.org !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Low Tech against the State</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/low-tech-against-the-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 20:14:44 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/low-tech-against-the-state/</guid>
      <description>Cumulative cultural evolution and the maladaptive loss of knowledge Humans are characterised as a specie by their exceptional ability for social learning. Indeed, while they are mostly unable to understand causally the tools they use, they are however able to identify who to learn from and what features to reproduce in a way that allow the maintenance and progress of their adaptive knowledge (Derex et al., 2019). In turn, this ability means that social structure &amp;amp; the sheer size of societies constrains the evolution of technology (Derex &amp;amp; Boyd, 2016) : more densely connected societies with a diversity of subpopulations are better able to maintain complex technologies such as ironwork than sparser or homogenous societies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theories of process, theories of things</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/theories-of-process-theories-of-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 21:42:23 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/theories-of-process-theories-of-things/</guid>
      <description>Cliodynamics and science-fiction Cliodynamics is a field which very existence is controversial. Among all subdisciplines of cultural evolution, it is the only one that consistently draw criticism every single time it is discussed - while its claims are by no mean stronger than those of early human history or cultural attraction theory. Two points may stroke as odd in such arguments : the first is that the very same thesis receive very different treatment if they are labeled &amp;ldquo;cliodynamics&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cultural evolution&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;historical anthropology&amp;rdquo; ; the second is that critics of cliodynamics rarely answer any specific point made by cliodynamicians, instead attributing them claims akin to Asimov&amp;rsquo;s psychohistory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond State</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/beyond-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 21:56:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/beyond-state/</guid>
      <description>States today seem to exert an undisputed hegemony over the governance of human societies. It seems natural to project their predominance on the past as well as on the future, or at least to imagine the world outside state regulation as wild, uncultivated, and unfit for human life. However, and against what seems obvious, States constitute a marginal and fragile mode of organization on the scale of human history. In the light of the work on the evolution of human societies over long period of time, it even seems doubtful whether these institutions will be able to maintain their dominance in the near future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognition in Eco, Cognition in Vitro</title>
      <link>http://kairos-research.org/articles/cognition-in-eco-cognition-in-vitro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 21:57:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://kairos-research.org/articles/cognition-in-eco-cognition-in-vitro/</guid>
      <description>The cognitive sciences are an interdisciplinary research project, built in the context of Macy&amp;rsquo;s conferences around the cognitivist paradigm that compares the functioning of the human mind with that of a computer. Sixty-seven years later, this project seems to have exploded between many competing approaches (Núñez et al., 2019), presumably under the abundant evidence of fundamental discrepancies between human cognition and artificial computation (Braitenberg, 1986; Brooks, 1991; Clark &amp;amp; Chalmers, 1998; Damasio, 1995; Varela et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>